<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Quakers shaken, or, A fire-brand snatch'd out of the fire being a briefe relation of Gods wonderful mercy extended to John Gilpin of Kendale in Westmoreland, who (as will appear by the sequel) was not onely deluded by the Quakers but also possessed by the Devill : if any question the truth of this story the relator himselfe is ready to avouch it, and much more.</title>
            <author>Gilpin, John, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42776</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G769</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36544</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15720696</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15720696</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104522</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42776)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104522)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1593:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Quakers shaken, or, A fire-brand snatch'd out of the fire being a briefe relation of Gods wonderful mercy extended to John Gilpin of Kendale in Westmoreland, who (as will appear by the sequel) was not onely deluded by the Quakers but also possessed by the Devill : if any question the truth of this story the relator himselfe is ready to avouch it, and much more.</title>
                  <author>Gilpin, John, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S.B. and are to be sold by Will. London, bookseller in Newcastle,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Gateside :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: John Gilpin.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104522:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE QVAKERS SHAKEN: OR, A Fire-brand ſnatch'd out of the Fire. BEING A briefe Relation of GODS won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull Mercy extended to JOHN GILPIN of <hi>KENDALE</hi> in WESTMORELAND. Who (as will appeare by the ſequel) was not onely deluded by the <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AKERS,</hi> but alſo poſſeſſed by the <hi>DEVILL.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any queſtion the Truth of this Story, the Relator himſelfe is ready to avouch it, and much more.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 24.4.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Take heed that no man deceive you, for many ſhall come in my Name, ſaying, I am Chriſt, and ſhall deceive many.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Cor. 11.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And no marvell, for Satan himſelfe is transformed into an Angell light.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Gateſide,</hi> Printed by <hi>S. B.</hi> and are to ſould by <hi>Will: London</hi> Book-ſeller in <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:104522:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104522:2"/>
            <head>THE QVAKERS <hi>SHAKEN.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He minde of man, deſtitute of Gods Grace, doth (like untilled ground) luxuruate into wickedneſſe and vanity, being very prone to cloſe with the ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions of the grand adverſary of his ſoule; yea, though he hath had ſome taſte of the things that are excellent; yet ſuch is his courteſie. that he will be ſeeking after Novelties. Old truths (like the <hi>Manna</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> after a conſtant and continued falling of it) become pauſeous: the truth hereof hath been found in all ages, by la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable experience; but eſpecially in theſe our dayes, which have been as fruitfull of new Opinions in matters of Religion, as <hi>Africa</hi> it ſelfe of Monſters.</p>
            <p>Some (though few in compariſon) God is pleaſed to recall, who have gone aſtray in this kind, and to bring them to a cleare ſight of their folly, of which number, I (by Gods Grace towards me) am one; I deſire to acknowledge him in it, and to give him the prayſe of it, and thinke my ſelfe bound in conſcience, as a teſtimony of my thankfulneſſe to God for my deliverance, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it to the world, that ſo others may heare, and feare, and take warning by my example. They who have been lately in the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne parts of <hi>England,</hi> cannot be ignorant how prevalent the impoſture of Quaking hath been for theſe nine or ten Moneths laſt paſt, in which ſnare I my ſelfe (among many poore deluded ſoules) was taken in <hi>May</hi> laſt 1653. though by Gods goodneſſe towards me, the ſnare is broaken, and I am eſcaped; a true ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count whereof, take as followeth.</p>
            <p>I being deſirous to aſſociate my ſelfe with this Faction at their Meeting, and to heare ſome of them ſpeake (to uſe their owne
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104522:3"/>expreſſion) acquainted one of their owne with it, <hi>viz. George Bayley</hi> of <hi>Kendale,</hi> who gave me great incouragement herein from his owne experience of much advantage received by him in that way: Whereupon I went ſoon after to their Meeting at <hi>Richard Newby's</hi> houſe, where I ſtayd about two houres (<hi>viz.</hi> from eight, till ten at night) where <hi>Chriſtopher Atkinſon</hi> was Speaker, whoſe drift was, to deny all Miniſteriall Teaching, and Ordinances, together with all notionall knowledge formerly gained by uſe of ſuch means, to become as though we had never learned any thing thereby ſavingly, and to lay a new ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke, <hi>viz.</hi> to be taught of God within our ſelves, by waiting upon an inward light, which (as they aſſert) lyes low hidden under the earth. <hi>viz.</hi> the old man which is of the Earth, Earthy. Hereupon I reſolved to cloſe with them; after which time I was afraid to reade any good Books, or heare any Preaching Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, or call to remembrance any thing which I had formerly learned out of Gods Word, concerning God or Chriſt, or mine owne eſtate, or any other ſubject contained in Scripture; for I was perſwaded by their teaching, that whatſoever I had learned out of Gods Word by Hearing, Reading, Catechizing, &amp;c. was but notionall, carnall, and hanging upon the Tree of Knowledge; in which condition whilſt I abode, they affirmed me to be under the Curſe, applying this expreſſion, though very impertinently, <hi>Curſed is every one that hangeth on the Tree.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this, going a ſecond time to one of their Meetings at <hi>Edmond Newby's,</hi> I had ſome conference by the way with ſome of themſelves which went with me; amongſt other Blaſphemies, one <hi>Robert Colliſon</hi> affirmed, That Chriſt was as man, had his fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, for he diſtruſted God (quoth he) upon the Croſſe, when he cryed out, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou ſorſaken me?</hi> To whom I anſwered, that then he ſuffered as an evill doer, and ſo could not purchaſe Redemption for us. After this, comming home, he who then was Speaker, urged us to take up the Croſſe dayly, and to abide under it; ſaying, <hi>Carry the Croſſe all day, and it will keep thee at night;</hi> that this would keep us low and humble, and kill and make alive; further, he endeavoured to perſwade his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, to hearken to a voyce within them; teaching, that Gods Voyce was a ſtill Voyce; after which I reſolved in my thoughts
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104522:3"/>to waite for the manifeſtation of theſe things within my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>After a while, going a third time to their Meeting, as I went, I was ſomewhat troubled in my thoughts at the remembrance of that hideous Blaſphemy, uttered by the party before named; whereupon I ſpake publiquely to them at their Meeting concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, telling them, That I would not any further joyne with them, if they were all of that mind; to which ſome of them (after much whiſpering) anſwered negatively, wiſhing me not to let it trouble me; for he which ſpake ſo to me, was not rightly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: with which anſwer, I was at preſent ſatisfied, and did adhere to my former reſolution. Not long after I went to another Meeting upon a Lords day at <hi>Robert Colliſons</hi> houſe in <hi>Kendale,</hi> where the aforeſaid <hi>Atkinſon</hi> was Speaker, who beginning about nine a clock in the forenoone, continued till three in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, in which time he ſpake much (according to his uſuall manner) of the great experience which he had of God from the light within him; which light I not finding to be in my ſelfe, was very much troubled, apprehending my condition to be very bad, finding nothing but blindneſſe and hardneſſe; yet I ſtill expected the appearance of that light within me, and earneſtly deſired that I might fall into quaking and trembling apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that I ſhould thereby attaine to the immediate diſcoveries of God unto me. Upon my departure from thence, I peruſed a Pamphlet ſet forth by ſome of the ſame Faction being in <hi>York-Caſtle,</hi> the maine ſcope of it was againſt the Miniſtry; immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after, walking in my Bed Chamber, I began (as I have formerly deſired) to tremble and quake ſo extreamely, that I could not ſtand upon my feet, but was conſtrained to fall down upon my Bed, where I howled and cryed (as it is uſuall with them) in a terrible and hideous manner, to the great aſtoniſhment of my Family; Nevertheleſſe I my ſelf was not at all affected with feare, becauſe it was a ſatisfaction to my former deſires, and I looked upon it as the beginning of the pangs of the new Birth, and expected that the iſſue of it would be good; when I had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued about halfe an houre in that condition, I ceaſed from howling and crying gradually; after which, I aroſe up againe beginning to rejoyce, thinking with my ſelfe, that now I could beare witneſſe againſt the Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> as falſe Prophets
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104522:4"/>and Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> becauſe I never found ſuch effects and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations upon me by ſo long continuance under their <hi>Miniſtery;</hi> After this, going to Bed, I was much troubled all that night fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in my ſleep, with dreames, concerning my condition, and had a diſcovery of my ſinnes in particular, eſpecially of Covetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, the Devill working ſtrongly upon my imagination; I apprehended that all ſinne was about to be hewed downe, and rooted up in me and (to my apprehenſion) the ſinne of Covetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe had great long roots, which did viſibly appeare to me when it was rooted up: Afterwards lying awake, and thinking upon the dreames and viſions I had formerly been troubled with, I ſenſibly perceived ſomething (as I imagined) lighting upon my neck, giving me a great ſtroke, which cauſed much paine to me; and after that another, which was leſſe then the firſt, and ſo a third and fourth, each ſtroke being leſſe then the former, and each ſtroke deſcending lower downe, till it came to the middle of my back, and then I thought ſomething entered into my body, which I perſwaded my ſelfe (from Satans inſtigation) to be the Spirit of God deſcending upon me like a Dove, and entring into me; whereupon I heard (in my conceit) a voyce within me ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>It is day;</hi> whereupon looking up, and perceiving it to be light, I anſwered, <hi>Yes;</hi> the Voyce teplyed twice over to me, and ſaid, <hi>As certain as it is light, ſo certainly ſhall Chriſt give thee light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this I continued two or three dayes wayting for further diſcoveries of light within me, being rapt up into an extaſie of exceſſive joy, and ſometimes againe exceedingly dejected with feares and doubts of my condition, whether it were really good, or I were under Satans deluſions; yet ſtill I wayted for further manifeſtations; and walking into the Garden, lying downe upon the ground with my Face towards the Earth, my right hand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan extreamely to ſhake, ſo as I could not hold it ſtill, the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whereof, whilſt I was wondering what it ſhould be, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending my ſelfe as being ſhaken by the hand, I was brought into another rapture of great joy, imagining it to be a figure of my ſpirituall Marriage and Union with Chriſt. Then preſently I was by the power within me rayſed, and ſet upon my Feet, and by the ſame power turned and layd upon my back, with my Face towards the Skie; at which time, all my ſinnes particularly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104522:4"/>were againe brought into my memory, and at the remembrance of every ſinne, my hand wa carryed round about, with giving a little pat upon the ground, and then I imagined I heard a Voyce ſaying, <hi>Now ſuch a ſinne is mortified;</hi> after which, <hi>I</hi> being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by it, that all my ſinnes were mortified by it one by one; the power that <hi>I</hi> was then acted by, permitted me to ariſe up againe of my ſelfe, ſaying unto me, <hi>Aske whatſoever thou wilt of the Father in my name, and he will give it thee:</hi> I replyed, <hi>I know not what to aske,</hi> and therefore deſired that power to teach me what <hi>I</hi> ſhould <hi>aske;</hi> he anſwered me againe, and bad me aske <hi>Wiſedome in the firſt place;</hi> whereupon <hi>I</hi> deſired alſo that God would give me ſuch things as were moſt for his glory, and the good of others; whereunto the power anſwered, <hi>That my requeſt was granted, and that I ſhould alſo be indewed with the gift of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, and ſinging prayſes to God;</hi> wherewith being ſatisfied; <hi>I</hi> went to another Meeting within an houre after, at <hi>William Dod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings</hi> houſe in <hi>Kendale,</hi> which was the fifth and laſt Meeting that <hi>I</hi> was at with them, where <hi>Chriſtopher Atkinſon</hi> being Speaker, <hi>I</hi> was much more affected with what he ſpake. then formerly, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able more inwardly to witnes in part to what he ſpoke. After he had done, and a little pauſe had, the company roſe up, as if they had been ready to depart; <hi>I</hi> my ſelfe was ready to goe away with the firſt, but the Wife of the houſe <hi>(Iſa. Dodding)</hi> tooke me by the hand; and wringing it very hard, had me ſit downe againe, which <hi>I</hi> did, and preſently after, one <hi>John Audland</hi> ſtood up, and began to ſpeake, ſaying, <hi>Cannot you watch one houre?</hi> and ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded after the uſuall manner. In the time of his ſpeaking, <hi>I</hi> was by the power within me, drawne from the Chaire upon which <hi>I</hi> ſate, and throwne upon the ground. in the middeſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, where <hi>I</hi> lay all Night; all which time, my body, and all the members of it, were ſtill in motion, <hi>I</hi> being turned from my backe to my belly, and ſo back againe ſeverall times, and making eroſſes continually, with my Leggs one over the other; my hands alſo were carried to and fro upon the ground by a compulſive power, as if <hi>I</hi> had been Writing upon the ground; in all which-actions and motions, <hi>I</hi> acted not in the leaſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure by a naturall power of mine owne, neither did <hi>I</hi> reſiſt, or could <hi>I</hi> reſiſt that power which acted me, but was altogether
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104522:5"/>paſſive, <hi>I</hi> was perſwaded that it was the immediate power of Chriſt, and heard, to my thinking, a Voyce ſpeaking to me, and ſaying, <hi>That that Writing with my hand upon the ground, did ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Writing of the Law within my heart.</hi> Having layne all Night upon the ground, in the manner aforeſaid, the power (as before in other actions) moved my hands to my head, and layd them upon the top thereof faſt cloſed together; whereupon <hi>I</hi> heard a Voyce ſaying, <hi>Chriſt in God, and God in Chriſt, and Chriſt in thee;</hi> which words <hi>I</hi> was compelled to ſing forth before the company in a ſtrange manner, and with ſuch a Voyce as was not naturally mine owne: <hi>I</hi> ſung alſo divers phraſes of Scripture, which were given into me: after which, <hi>I</hi> was rayſed from the ground, and ſet upon my Feet by the power within me, which bad me be humble, and brought me downe againe upon my knees, and with a whiſpering Voyce ſaid to me, <hi>Stoope low, low;</hi> and having ſtooped neere the ground with my Face, it ſaid to me, <hi>Take up thy Croſſe and follow me;</hi> whereupon ariſing. <hi>I</hi> was led out of the houſe (by the back dore) downe to the River, and back againe from thence into the Towne another way where <hi>I</hi> was ſenſibly drawne downe the ſtreet, and cauſed ſuddenly to turne aſide to a doore of an houſe (my ſelfe not knowing who lived in it) two of the ſaid company following me all the time, <hi>(viz.) William Dodding,</hi> and <hi>John Audland,</hi> and ſeeing me to goe to that door. ſaid, <hi>Whether wilt thou goe? this is the Fidlers houſe; I</hi> anſwered <hi>Whoſe houſe ſoever it be, Chriſt leads me hither, and hither I muſt goe;</hi> whereupon my hand was carryed to <hi>knocke</hi> at the doore, and commanded by a Voyce to ſay, <hi>Behold, Chriſt ſtands at the doore and knockes;</hi> after a while the Fidler opened, and <hi>I</hi> was led into the houſe, not ſpeaking any thing unto him, where my hand was carryed to a Bace-Violl, hanging up in the houſe; I tooke it downe, and began to play upon it with my fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and was immediately compelled to fall a dancing. which <hi>I</hi> ſeldome or never in all my life did before; hereupon I queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned what power it ſhould be that carryed me forth to ſuch acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to which the Voyce within me replyed, <hi>This is not becauſe I love Muſicke, for I hate it; but to ſignifie unto thee what joy there is in Heaven at thy converſion; as alſo, what ſpirituall Melody then ſhalt have hereafter:</hi> Then I was led out of the houſe into
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104522:5"/>the ſtreet, and ſo carried along through the Towne, being moved to Proclaime as I went, <hi>I am the way the truth, and the life,</hi> with other expreſſions to like purpoſe; after which, I was brought to mine own houſe, the aforeſaid <hi>William Dodding</hi> going along with me, acknowledged, that he had no power to leave me all this time; being come home, the ſame power would not ſuffer me to reſt, but caſt me upon the ground and cauſed me to make Circles round about the houſe with my hand, with many the like actions, telling me, <hi>that I was putting off the old man;</hi> my hand alſo was carryed to take up a ſtone which lay upon the floore (which in my apprehenſion was in the forme of a mans heart) the Voyce within me telling me, <hi>That Chriſt had taken that ſtone out of my heart, and given me an heart of fleſh,</hi> and my hand was moved to hold it forth to the ſpectators, and my tongue to utter this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, <hi>Except you ſee ſignes and wonders you will not beleeve;</hi> and throwing the aforeſaid ſtone amongſt them, I ſaid, <hi>Loe, here is my heart of ſtone;</hi> afterwards, being caſt upon the ground upon my backe, the Voyce ſpake to me, ſaying, <hi>Thou ſhalt have two An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels to keep thee,</hi> whereupon immediately two Swallows deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded downe the Chimney, and ſate upon a ſhelfe over againſt the place where <hi>I</hi> lay; this, others in the houſe beſides my ſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, and <hi>I</hi> cryed to them, <hi>My Angels, my Angels,</hi> being perſwaded that they were Angels from Heaven, and that it was a fulfilling the promiſe; <hi>I</hi> held out my hand towards them, expecting they ſhould have come to me, but they did not, but aſcended up the Chimney, though both the doore and the window were open.</p>
            <p>I was alſo by the ſame power carryed out of doores upon my hands and knees into the ſtreet which my Wife and other ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, endeavoured to hinder me. but <hi>I</hi> told them, <hi>I</hi> would not be hindred, but leave Wife, Children, and all to follow Chriſt; in his manner <hi>I</hi> went up the ſtreet, thinking that <hi>I</hi> bore a Croſſe upon my neck, and continued in this motion, till ſome pulled me out of the mire and durt, and by force carried me into the houſe againe; whereupon <hi>I</hi> was moved to point to one of them which brought me in, and to ſay to her, <hi>Chriſt points at thee, thou art a wicked woman, and haſt hindered the worke of the Lord;</hi> then one Voyce asked me <hi>where my Croſſe was,</hi> telling me, <hi>I had ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ered it,</hi> whereupon <hi>I</hi> was moved to make a Croſſe with my fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104522:6"/>upon the floore, and forced to ſet my head upon it, playing topſie turvie, or bull necks, thinking then I had re-taken up my Croſſe; in theſe actions I was kept a long while, having many Scripture expreſſions given me, to the admiration of all that heard me; ſometimes I was forced to leape and dance, this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion being given in to me, <hi>Now I have finiſhed the worke which thou gaveſt me to doe,</hi> thinking my Redemption then fully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed; but my joy continued not, for I was caſt downe againe, and the Voyce told me, <hi>I had offended God in attributing that to my ſelfe, which was proper to Chriſt;</hi> whereupon I was caſt upon the ground, and lying upon my belly, I was forced to lick the duſt, and my hand carried to ſtrike extraordinarily up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my head, having a Voyce given me, <hi>That no ſinne muſt goe unpuniſhed;</hi> ſo creeping up and downe the houſe, I heard a Voyce ſaying, <hi>Where is thy Croſſe?</hi> upon which, looking aſide, I thought I ſaw a viſible Croſſe hanging in a thread, which with my hand I put behinde my neck; I was kept in theſe poſtures all that day till evening, when many <hi>Quakers</hi> came in to me, who ſpake no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but thus, <hi>Be lowly, mind thy condition, and hearken to the voyce within;</hi> not giving any words of comfort or reproofe, or put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up any Petition at all for me, but departed, leaving me in this condition; my ſtrength being almoſt ſpent, and my body much conſumed by continuall reſtleſſeneſſe: Two of them of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to watch with me that Night, but I refuſed, talling them I was well, whereupon they departed. After this, my Wife and Family being gone to Bed, <hi>I</hi> being alone in the houſe, began to recollect my ſelfe, and to queſtion whether that power by which I had been ſo ſtrangely acted, were Divine, or Diabolicall? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I was immediately ſtruck with a pannick feare, and my hand was carried to take up a Knife which lay upon the Table, which being done, my hand was carried with it towards my throat, and the Voyce ſaid to me, <hi>Open a hole there, and I will give thee the words of eternall life;</hi> whereupon I anſwered, <hi>What, with a Knife?</hi> and ſo threw the Knife away, being confident it was a temptation, from which I deſire God to deliver me: My Wife being in Bed in the next Roome, and hearing me ſpeake when none was with me, came out, and deſired me to goe to Bed, which <hi>I</hi> did, at her entreaty: all the Night following <hi>I</hi> was fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104522:6"/>that it was the Devils power that had acted me all along formerly, and was perſwaded that <hi>I</hi> was really poſſeſt with a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, which muſt be ejected; and in the morning <hi>I</hi> verily thought that a Devill went out of me, at which inſtant <hi>I</hi> roared very hidiouſly, crying, <hi>Now is the Devill gone out of me,</hi> at which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, I and my Family heard it thunder, (though none in the Towne beſides, heard it) which made me thinke it was the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, <hi>he being the Prince of the power of the Ayre;</hi> ſoon after, the ſame power came under another notion, and told me, <hi>That it was Satan that had poſſeſt and led me heretofore, but now Chriſt was come, and he by his power had caſt oui Satan, and convinced me, that what ever I had done the day before, was in obedience to Satan, and that as I had ſerved the Devill all the day before in my clothes, ſo that day I muſt undoe all that I had formerly done, onely in my ſhirt in Obedience to Chriſt;</hi> which immediately I endeavoured, riſing out of my Bed, and going into the ſtreet with my ſhirt onely; but my Wife and others, ſoone layd hold upon me, and ſtopt me; whereupon, the power within me, told me, <hi>That I muſt be carried into the houſe with foure women, as I had been the day before, or elſe I ſhould perpetually ſtand there like a pillar of Salt, as</hi> Lots <hi>Wife did:</hi> So I was borne in by foure women, who carried me again into my bed; which being done, I told them, <hi>I had been doing the Devils worke the day before, but to day</hi> I <hi>muſt doe the worke of Chriſt,</hi> and point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at a woman, whom I had pointed at the day before, ſaid theſe words, <hi>the Devill told me yeſterday that you were a wicked woman; but now Chriſt tels me that you are Gods Servant;</hi> the Woman being departed, I fell to acting in my ſhirt onely, upon the bed, as I had done formerly upon the houſe floore, playing topſie turvie from one bed to another, whereby I might have undone my ſelfe; but the power which acted me, bid me not feare, <hi>for I will give thee ſtrentgh.</hi> After this, the power told me, <hi>that the Devill had the other day commanded me to beare my Croſſe; but now Chriſt commands thee to lay aſide thy Croſſe, for Chriſt takes no pleaſure in Croſſes, nor will he have me worſhip them, as yeſterday I had done:</hi> Further, the power ſaid to me, <hi>the Devill made thee yeſter day to lye all day upon the ground, but now I have provided a bed for thee,</hi> giving in this Scripture to me, <hi>My yoke is eaſie;</hi> promiſing alſo, <hi>to give me bread of life to eat, and water of life to drinke, and that out of my belly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104522:7"/>ſhould flow Rivers of living Water;</hi> whereupon my teeth wer cauſed to move, as if I had been eating; and I thought I felt is my belly a flowing up and downe, as of waters; I was alſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that yeſterday the Devils Angels had waited on me, but now Chriſts Angels ſhould guard me; whereupon I ſaw two Butter-flyes in the window, to which my hand was carried, and having taken one of them in my hand, I was moved by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er within me to put it into my mouth and did ſwallow it downe into my body; which having done, I tooke the other in my hand, and was moved to put it to my throat; the power telling me, <hi>it ſhould enter in there</hi> ſaying, <hi>nothing is impoſſible to them that be leeve.</hi> After this I was cauſed to make Circles upon the bed as <hi>I</hi> had done formerly upon the ground; whereupon <hi>I</hi> began to think that this was not of God, and ſo began to reſiſt the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er by which I was acted, and thereupon fell into great feare and doubting crying out, <hi>Lord what wilt thou have me to doe?</hi> but the power told me, <hi>that it was too late to cry unto God, for ſentence was already pronounced againſt me;</hi> whereupon <hi>I</hi> lay downe in my bed much deſpairing, and was then convinct that it was the Devill which had againe deluded me; in which condition having layne a ſhort ſpace, I was againe aſſaulted by a power the third time, which told me, <hi>that it was a white Devill that had received me the latter time, but now Chriſt was come indeed, and he would caſt him out;</hi> whereupon <hi>I</hi> apprehended that Devill alſo to be ejected, after which, as I law in my bed all the members of my body fell a working as if the pangs of death had been upon me the power telling me, <hi>that it was the pangs of the new birth and that Chriſt was new borne in me,</hi> with which I was ſomewhat ſatisfied, lying in that condition a whole day; in which time the power perſwaded me, <hi>that</hi> I <hi>ſhould worke wonders, and caſt out Devils in his name</hi> Soon after two <hi>Quakers</hi> came to me, <hi>viz. Geo Bryley</hi> &amp; I, <hi>Braban,</hi> whom I told that I had had two Devils caſt out of me, but now Chriſt was in me for a truth, then the power (pretending to be Chriſt) ſaid theſe words, <hi>I was crowned with a crown of thornes but I will crown thee with a crown of glory</hi> and bad me (as a figure therof) <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſet my fiſt upon my head, and it ſhould appeare to the ſtanders by as a glorious crown, though</hi> I <hi>ſaw nothing my ſelfe;</hi> which having done I ſpake to the ſtanders by, ſaying, <hi>what doe you ſee?</hi> whereunto they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104522:7"/>gave me no anſwer (being Quakers) but turned their eies another way, the power telling me, <hi>that they ſaw the crown upon my head; but were ſo ſtrucken with admiration that they could not expreſſe what they ſaw;</hi> immediately the power had me till one of the Quakers then preſent, <hi>that he had a devil in him, and that I ſhould have power to caſt him out;</hi> whereupon I ſaid to him, <hi>G thou haſt a Divell in thee,</hi> the power told me he ſhould <hi>quake and tremble</hi> which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately he did; the power bade me ſpeake to him <hi>to fall flat upon the ground</hi> which he did, and after a little ſpace roſe againe, and I asked him <hi>whether the devil were gone out of him</hi> (having been before perſwaded by the power that I ſhould caſt him out) to which he gave me no anſwer but the power told me <hi>that the Devill was ejected;</hi> I was told alſo by the ſame power, who (of thoſe that came to ſee me) <hi>had devills, and who not; and that my wife and my mother had devills in them, but I had power given me to caſt them out.</hi> After this beginning againe to queſtion whether this were Chriſt or not, I fell into great feare and doubting as formerly; whereupon the devil diſcovered himſelf to be the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and told me, <hi>that all this while I had been ſerving him, and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming God, and that it was now too late to repent,</hi> whereupon I was brought into deſpaire for a time, thinking every thing which <hi>I</hi> either heard or ſaw, to be the Devil come to fetch me away: one while I thought that I ſhould be taken away in a flame of fire or elſe that the earth would ſwallow me up quick; whereupon <hi>I</hi> called my wife and deſired her to bring up my children in the feare of God, for the devill would fetch me away, my ſelfe ſtill thinking that he was drawing me out of the bed; thus <hi>I</hi> appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended my ſelfe wholly under the power of the devil, and had no power to recover my ſelfe out of that ſad condition. At laſt <hi>I</hi> began (having been ſo long deluded) to deſiſt from hearkning to the voyce within me and apply my ſelf unto God, in &amp; through Chriſt, for deliverance from the power of Satan, knowing that God was able to deliver me, though <hi>I</hi> were ſo farre involved in the ſnare of the devill, thereupon my faith was in ſome meaſure raiſed to beleeve that God would deliver me; whereupon I was preſently in a great agonie and did ſweat extreamly, in which condition I continued all night, but was ſomewhat more chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the morning eſteeming my ſelfe in ſome meaſure reſcued
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104522:8"/>from the power of the devill: yet having not reſolved, as yet fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to deſert that way, I was ſoone againe aſſaulted by the ſame power, telling me, <hi>that now the devil was finally caſt out of me, and that the roome within me muſt not be left empty, but that Chriſt muſt come and have the whole, &amp; ſole poſſeſſion, or elſe Satan would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn and re-enter with ſeven other Devils worſe then himſelfe,</hi> telling me withall <hi>that he was Chriſt,</hi> and ſolliciting me to entertaine and imbrace him as he had done formerly: I reſiſted the ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this power for a time, having ben ſo often deluded; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon as a motive to perſwade me to entertain it, he repreſented to my memorie all, or moſt of the remarkable paſſages of my life, both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> told me how long I ſhould live, <hi>viz.</hi> ten yeares, and where I ſhould die, <hi>viz.</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> and that I had a weak bodie, but he would ſtrengthen it, and thereupon cauſed me to rub my bodie all over with my hands, at which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant I conceived my bodie to receive ſtrength, and the members thereof to be more in ſubſtance then before; with divers other paſſages, promiſing me proſperitie in the world, and ſpeaking theſe words to me <hi>John</hi> 4.29, <hi>Behold, a man that hath told thee all things that ever thou didſt, is not this Chriſt?</hi> whereupon I was at laſt perſwaded to imbrace this power, thinking that it was Chriſt indeed; whereupon I was preſently ſenſible of a working throughout my whole bodie, which ſoone ceaſed, and then I thought that my condition was good, and Chriſt to be really in me: afterwards this power told me, that J had highly offended God in all my formes paſſages in giving way to Satan, and that I was guiltie of all ſins except that againſt the holy Ghoſt, but told me, that I did it ignorantly, and therefore he had pitty on me; I was further perſwaded by the ſame power, that J ſhould lie (ſeemingly) dead, which I did, not daring to ſtirre, til the power moved me. Lying thus a while, the power began firſt to move one of my legs, and then the other; after that my hands, and then my head, and at laſt my whole bodie; cauſing me to ſit up in my bed; and telling me, <hi>that thus ſhould my body be quickened and raiſed up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain at the laſt day:</hi> then the power told me, <hi>that</hi> I <hi>muſt pull off my ſhirt, and my cap, and the napkin which</hi> I <hi>had about my neck,</hi> ſaying <hi>that whatſoever was about me was polluted, and that he hated the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſpotted with the fleſh;</hi> whereupon I pull'd them off, and threw
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104522:8"/>them on the ground, uttering theſe ſame words, <hi>that I hated the garments ſpoted with the fleſh:</hi> the power alſo told me, <hi>that all my bonds were broken, and my cords looſened, and that Chriſt had ſet me free;</hi> whereupon calling for a clean ſhirt, and other linnen, I aroſe; concluding my ſelfe to be in a good condition; yet finding my ſelf being up, no better, nor my bodie more ſtrengtheed, but rather weakened, J began to ſee that I had been deluded in this laſt buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe as formerly; whereupon I was ſtrucken with fear, and walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the Garden, I thought one while that the Divell would pull me into the earth, and another while that he would pull me into the aire, ſo that I was afraid to continue abroad, and came againe into the houſe, and ſuſpected every thing that I heard to be the Devil waiting to fetch me away; being in this perplexitie of ſoule, I began to conſider how grievouſly I had offended God in rejecting the uſe of all externall means; as reading, hearing, prayer, &amp;c. in the uſe whereof God hath commanded us to wait upon him, and therefore that it was moſt juſt with him to leave me to my ſelfe, and to give me over to ſtrong deluſion, that I ſhould beleeve lies, which was my condition for a time, by the juſt judgement of God upon me, as for other provocations, ſo eſpecially for rejecting the revealed will of God in his Word, and hearkning only to a voice within me; becauſe what was ſpoken by it, was ſeconded by lying Wonders, of which God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven notice in his Word, that ſo his people might not give credit to them, nor be deluded by them. I hope the Reader will ſo farre give heed to what I have related concerning my ſelfe, as to learn thereby to take heed of being impoſed upon by the devil, though he doth transforme himſelfe into an angell of light; which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage if any reape by it, I have my end: it hath been no ſmall burthen to my conſcience (ſince Gods gracious deliverance of me from this ſnare) that I ſhould ſo farre gratifie the grand Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſarie, as not onely to liſten to his ſuggeſtions, and embrace his voice for the voice of Chriſt, but alſo wholly to neglect thoſe meanes, in the conſtant and conſcientious uſe whereof God hath promiſed to reveale himſelfe unto his people, and to give in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to them, which becauſe I found not (though through my owne deſault) I did in effect ſay, <hi>why ſhould</hi> I <hi>waite for the Lord any longer?</hi> and ſo turned unto lying vanities. Oh, that all who
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104522:9"/>affect novelties, would ſeriouſly conſider of it, and take warning by it; for, <hi>Turpius ejicitur quam non admittitur:</hi> It is eaſier to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the devill at his firſt aſſault, then to expell him being once admitted. Many beſides my ſelf, have bin, and are in the like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diton but few or none to whom the Lord hath manifeſted his Grace in ſuch a manner as to my ſelfe: <hi>I</hi> had before this made this known to the world, had I had tranquillitie of conſcience, and compoſure of ſpirit; which bleſſing, the Lord having in his grace reſtored to me, <hi>I</hi> deſire the Chriſtian Reader to joyne with me in returning praiſes unto the Lord for his goodneſs towards me; I reſt fully perſwaded, and I think it doth evidently appear (by what is mentioned in this Relation) to perſons unprejudiced, that my quaking and trembling was of the devill, that I was acted, wholly and ſolely by him whilſt in this condition, and I doe really beleeve, that others in the like condition which I was then in would be of the ſame mind with me upon ſerious tryall of their condition by the principles of Chriſtian Religion, and ſanctified Reaſon; leaſt the ſtrangeneſſe of ſome paſſages in this Relation, ſhould put the faith of any one upon the racke or make them queſtion the truth thereof; <hi>I</hi> have not onely given teſtimonie my ſelfe of it, by ſubſcribing my name, but alſo procured ſeveral, perſons of known fidelity living in, or neere <hi>Kendale,</hi> (whoſe names are under-writen) to teſtifie the probabilitie (if not, the certaintie) of the truth of it, by what they have ſeen and heard.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOHN GLPIN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_names">
            <list>
               <item>I beleeve this Relation to be true, <hi>Edward Turner</hi> Mayor of <hi>Kendale.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>By what <hi>J</hi> have heard of the carriage of <hi>John Gilpin,</hi> and his actings, <hi>I</hi> do beleeve this Relation to be true, <hi>John Archer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>I ſaw him when he went through the Towne, declaring himſelfe the way, truth, and life. <hi>Ja. Cocke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>We beleeve this Relation to be true.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>T. Walker,</hi> Paſtor of <hi>Kendale.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>J. Myriell,</hi> Maſter of the Free-Schoole there.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rich. Priſſoe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Sands.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Allan Gilpin.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Waſhington.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rob. Fiſher.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:104522:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
